<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE tmx SYSTEM "tmx11.dtd">
<tmx version="1.1">
  <header creationtool="OmegaT" o-tmf="OmegaT TMX" adminlang="EN-US" datatype="plaintext" creationtoolversion="6.0.1_0_42ef0143" segtype="sentence" srclang="en-US"/>
  <body>
<!-- Default translations -->
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>## Conclusion</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200246Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200246Z">
        <seg>Conclusión</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>## The *Bildungsroman* and the humanist tradition</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T203128Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203128Z">
        <seg>El Bildungsroman y la tradición humanista.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>(1936–38).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T204857Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T204857Z">
        <seg>(1936–38).
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>(2004, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T182804Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T193246Z">
        <seg>(2004, p.(2004,p.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>(A novel of de-formation:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T154236Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T154236Z">
        <seg>Una novela de de-formación: </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>(rational human subjects) and res extensa (lifeless objects, including animals).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T182944Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T182944Z">
        <seg>(sujetos humanos racionales) y la res extensa (objetos inertes, incluidos los animales).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>*Liber Amoris* with some graduate students and found that they had no understanding whatever of Hazlitt’s obsessive commitment to Sarah Walker.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001250Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001250Z">
        <seg>Liber Amoris con algunos estudiantes de posgrado y comprobé que no tenían la más mínima comprensión del compromiso obsesivo de Hazlitt hacia Sarah Walker.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>No agregar espacios tras el punto</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>*Lolita* is about love.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T215106Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T215106Z">
        <seg>Lolita trata sobre el amor. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>1), which is “linked to *Humanität* as harmonious development of individuality” through “a metamorphoses of role and character” (Ryan et al., 2022).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T203920Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203920Z">
        <seg>1), el cual está «vinculado a la Humanität en el desarrollo armónico de la individualidad» mediante «una metamorfosis del rol y del carácter» (Ryan et al., 2022).
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>136)
:::</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T193847Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T193847Z">
        <seg>136).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>157) constitutes</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T183155Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T183155Z">
        <seg>157) constituye </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>1906 study *Poetry and Experience* that the term gained traction in modern criticism (Boes, 2006, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T203652Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203652Z">
        <seg>estudio Poesía y experiencia de 1906 (Boes, 2006, p. 231).
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Aguantar las oraciones largas (no son necesarias las rayas)</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>2020_ and I looked and looked at her, and knew as clearly as I know I am to die, that I loved her more than anything I had ever seen or imagined on earth, or hoped for anywhere else.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184759Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184759Z">
        <seg>; y yo la miraba y la miraba, y sabía —con la misma certeza con que sé que he de morir— que la amaba más que a cualquier cosa que hubiese visto o imaginado en la tierra, o hubiese esperado en ningún otro lugar. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>23), which he identiﬁes as the focal point of the genre in “The Bildungsroman and Its Signiﬁcance in the History of Realism”</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T204831Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T204703Z">
        <seg>23), que lo identifica como el punto central del género en «El Bildungsroman y su significado en la historia del realismo»
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>230–231).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T210047Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T210047Z">
        <seg>230-231).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>29; italics in the original).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T204345Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T204345Z">
        <seg>29; cursivas en el original).
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>4), operates as one of the emblems of the doctrine of humanism.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T191402Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T191402Z">
        <seg>4), opera como uno de los emblemas de la doctrina humanista.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>4, italics in the original)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T183115Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T183115Z">
        <seg>4, cursivas en el original).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>6), which is itself a corollary of the postmodern crisis of subjectivity.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200607Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200607Z">
        <seg>6), la cual es un corolario de la crisis posmoderna de la subjetividad.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>7), or in Beville’s terms, “those obstacles to subjective knowledge and the creation of coherent identity” (2009, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T174823Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T174823Z">
        <seg>7), o, por lo que respecta a Beville, «aquellos obstáculos para el conocimiento subjetivo y la creación de una identidad coherente» (2009, p. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>8), the latter of which is the one used in this study because of its correspondence to Dilthey’s deﬁnition of the genre.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T204540Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T204540Z">
        <seg>8), y el segundo es el que se emplea en este estudio debido a la equivalencia con la definición del género propuesta por Dilthey.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>90), it dissents from Dilthey’s insistence on its peculiarity to German literature.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T190401Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T190401Z">
        <seg>90), se aparta de la insistencia de Dilthey en lo relativo a su especificidad dentro del ámbito de la literatura alemana. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>:::{.Quotation centered}
(1) the idea of &lt;u&gt;Bildung&lt;/u&gt;, or formation… shaping of a single main character, normally of a young man; (2) individualism, especially the emphasis on the uniqueness of the protagonist and the primacy of his private life and thoughts, although these are at the same time representative of an age and culture; (3) the biographical element… in what Dilthey calls the ‘conscious and artistic presentation of what is typically human through the depiction of a particular individual life’; (4) the connection with psychology, especially the then-new psychology of development; and (5) the ideal of humanity, of the full realization of all human potential as the goal of life.’ (1968, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T193818Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T193818Z">
        <seg>(1) el concepto de Bildung, o formación, que le da forma a un solo personaje principal, por lo general un joven; (2) el individualismo, en especial el énfasis en la singularidad del protagonista y la primacía de su vida y pensamientos íntimos, aunque estos son, al mismo tiempo, representativos de una época y una cultura; (3) el elemento biográfico, en lo que Dilthey denomina la «presentación consciente y artística de lo que es típicamente humano a través de la descripción de una vida individual en particular»; (4) la conexión con la psicología, en especial con la nueva psicología del desarrollo de aquel entonces; y (5) el ideal de humanidad, de la plena realización de todo el potencial humano como meta de vida.’ (1968, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>A Literary Companion* (2010), Hage argues that *Child of God* is “as much bildungsroman as work of grotesque horror; it just happens to be about a serial killer” (p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T161751Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T161751Z">
        <seg>A Literary Companion (2010), Hage sostiene que El hijo de Dios es “tanto una novela de formación como una obra de terror grotesco; simplemente trata sobre un asesino serial”.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>ARTICLE</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T182852Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T182852Z">
        <seg>ARTÍCULO</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Above all, the Gothic degeneration of the setting crystallizes in Ballard’s habitation shifts from a relatively civilized house to a cave, a cage, the dissection table of a medical school, a plastic bag, and ultimately a remote cemetery reserved for outcasts.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200900Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200900Z">
        <seg>Sobre todo, la degeneración gótica del escenario se cristaliza en los cambios de morada de Ballard, que pasan de una casa relativamente civilizada a una cueva, a una jaula, a la mesa de disección de una facultad de medicina, a una bolsa de plástico y, al final, a un cementerio lejano reservado para los marginados.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>According to Jerold E. Hogle, Kristeva argues that “grotesques” were “explicitly created to embody [the] contradictions” and indeterminacy of our identities (2002, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T174740Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T174740Z">
        <seg>Según Jerold E. Hogle, Kristeva sostiene que los «grotescos» han sido «creados explícitamente para personificar [las] contradicciones» y la indeterminación de nuestras identidades (2002, p. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>According to Rosi Braidotti, humanism “combines the biological, discursive and moral expansion of human capabilities into an idea of teleologically ordained, rational progress” (2013, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T191305Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T191305Z">
        <seg>Según Rosi Braidotti, el humanismo «combina la expansión biológica, discursiva y moral de las capacidades humanas en una idea de progreso racional teleológicamente orientado» (2013, p. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>According to Tobias Boes, the term Bildungsroman was ﬁrst coined by a professor of rhetoric called Karl Morgenstern in a lecture entitled</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T203312Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203312Z">
        <seg>El profesor de retórica Karl Morgensten acuña el término Bildungsroman por primera vez en una conferencia dictada en 1810 titulada</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Accordingly, it is easy to discern the imbrication between the thematic concerns of the *Bildungsroman* and such humanist notions as self-acculturation, self-empowering reason, mastery, social integration, and harmony.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T182731Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T182731Z">
        <seg>En consecuencia, resulta posible advertir con claridad la imbricación entre las preocupaciones temáticas del Bildungsroman y nociones humanistas tales como la autoformación cultural, la razón empoderada, el dominio, la integración social y la armonía.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Accordingly, the disturbing playfulness of the Gothic that complements postmodern parody disrupts the typical path of the Bildungsroman toward positive development and social incorporation.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200734Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200734Z">
        <seg>En consecuencia, el inquietante carácter lúdico de lo gótico, que complementa la parodia posmoderna, perturba el recorrido típico del Bildungsroman hacia el desarrollo positivo y la incorporación social. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Accordingly, the present study stakes out a new terrain in postmodern Gothic studies by establishing a line of communication between the Gothic, postmodernism, and the tradition of the Bildungsroman based on their relationship with the discourse of humanism.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T154915Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T154915Z">
        <seg>En consecuencia, el presente artículo marca un nuevo terreno en los estudios posmodernos góticos mediante el establecimiento de una línea de comunicación entre el estilo gótico, el posmodernismo y la tradición de la novela de formación basada en la relación que tiene con el discurso del humanismo. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Sentido</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Alanus Capellanus in his manual on courtly love set it down as perfectly obvious doctrine that a husband and wife cannot be lovers.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T220604Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T220604Z">
        <seg>En su manual acerca del amor cortesano, Alanus Capellanus establece una doctrina totalmente obvia en la que el marido y la mujer no pueden ser amantes. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>personificación</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Almost every page sets forth some explicit erotic emotion or some overt erotic action and still it is not about sex.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T215214Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T215214Z">
        <seg>Casi cada página describe alguna emoción erótica explícita o alguna acción erótica evidente y, aun así, no trata sobre el sexo. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Although Davies stresses the protean and elusive nature of the concept, it is possible to demarcate some of its constitutive convictions, which extensively overlap with Enlightenment ideals as one of its phases.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T191257Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T191257Z">
        <seg>Si bien Davies subraya la naturaleza proteica y escurridiza del concepto, es posible delimitar algunas de sus convicciones constitutivas, que se solapan en gran medida con los ideales ilustrados en tanto una de sus fases.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Although the term “humanism” resists a single uniﬁed deﬁnition, the deﬁnitional framework used in this study focuses on the Western ideal of Man formulated by “Protagoras as ‘the measure of all things’” with bodily normativity and a capacity for mental perfectibility, which constitutes the warp and woof of the humanist conception of subjectivity (Braidotti, 2013, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T191153Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T191153Z">
        <seg>Aunque el término «humanismo» se resiste a una definición unívoca, el marco definitivo adoptado en este estudio se centra en el ideal Occidental del hombre formulado por «Protágoras como “la medida de todas las cosas”», dotado de normatividad corporal y de una capacidad de perfectibilidad mental, lo cual constituye la urdimbre y la trama de la concepción humanista de la subjetividad (Braidotti, 2013, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Although this study employs the ﬁve characteristics stated by Dilthey and his deﬁnition of the *Bildungsroman* as “a type of novel that portrayed personal emergence simultaneously as a psychological maturation and social integration” (Graham, 2019, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T204956Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T204956Z">
        <seg>Si bien este estudio emplea las cinco características señaladas por Dilthey y su definición del Bildungsroman como «un tipo de novela que retrata el surgimiento personal tanto en términos de maduración psicológica como de una integración social» (Graham, 2019, p</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Although various studies have explored certain aspects of the novel appertaining to identity and the psychological formation of the protagonist,1 the relationship between the novel and the tradition of the *Bildungsroman* vis-à-vis human subjectivity has been afforded scant critical attention.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T161641Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T161641Z">
        <seg>A pesar de que diversos estudios exploraron ciertos aspectos de la novela relacionados con la identidad y la formación psicológica del protagonista, la relación entre la novela y la tradición del género bildungsroman frente a la subjetividad humana fue objeto de escaso análisis crítico.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>And builds a Hell in</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T002452Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T002452Z">
        <seg>Y construye un infierno 
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>And builds a Hell in Heaven s despite.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Gabriel" changedate="20260407T170913Z" creationid="Gabriel" creationdate="20260407T170913Z">
        <seg>Y construye un infierno en medio del cielo».</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Reponer cursiva. Pensar el sentido de la estructura de amused</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>And in nothing is Lolita so archaic as in its way of imaging the beloved.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001750Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001750Z">
        <seg>Y en nada resulta Lolita tan arcaico como en su manera de imaginar al ser amado.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>And in the end H. H. succumbs, and happily, to the dialectic of the history of love.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184436Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184436Z">
        <seg>Y al final H. H. sucumbe —y con gusto— a la dialéctica de la historia del amor. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>avisar si hay segmentos truncados.</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>And it is just this that</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Gabriel" changedate="20260407T171655Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184551Z">
        <seg>Y es precisamente esto lo que H. H. acaba por desear.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>And it is just this that H. H. eventually desires.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Gabriel" changedate="20260407T174031Z" creationid="Gabriel" creationdate="20260407T174031Z">
        <seg>Y es precisamente esto lo que H. H. acaba por desear </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Modalización</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Apart from this, every aspect of the new relationship is a denial of the old ideal of love.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221233Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221233Z">
        <seg>Además, cada aspecto de la nueva relación supone una negación del antiguo ideal del amor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Aristocratic excess, though still in evidence, is generally replaced by other forms of threat.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T024519Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T024519Z">
        <seg>El exceso aristocrático, aunque aún está presente, se reemplaza, por lo general, por otras formas de amenaza.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Aristocratic trappings of chivalry and romance are subsumed by bourgeois values of virtue, merit, propriety and, within reason, individualism.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T024140Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T024140Z">
        <seg>Los símbolos aristocráticos de la caballería y el romance quedan subordinados a los valores burgueses de virtud, mérito, decoro y, dentro de lo razonable, al individualismo.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>As Paul Sheehan aptly puts it, the Bildungsroman is “essential to an emplotment of the transactions between the human (humanism, humanitas) and the novel”</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T182750Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T182750Z">
        <seg>Como señala con acierto Paul Sheehan, el Bildungsroman es «esencial para la configuración narrativa de las transacciones entre lo humano (humanism, humanitas) y la novela»</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>As Tony Davies argues, although some of the notions frequently associated with the tradition of humanism can be traced back to the Renaissance, the term was coined for the ﬁrst time by Enlightenment scholars, such as Friedrich Immanuel Niethammer, in Germany in the nineteenth century (1997, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T191230Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T191230Z">
        <seg>Como sostiene Tony Davies, aunque algunas de las nociones frecuentemente asociadas con la tradición humanista pueden rastrearse hasta el Renacimiento, el término fue acuñado por primera vez por eruditos de la Ilustración, como Friedrich Immanuel Niethammer, en Alemania en el siglo XIX (1997, p</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>As a literary tradition intimately intertwined with the teleological discourse of humanism, the *Bildungsroman* or the novel of formation can provide an optimal point of departure for participation in the contemporary debate on human subjectivity.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T154823Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T154823Z">
        <seg>Como tradición literaria ligada íntimamente al discurso teleológico del humanismo, el género bildungsroman o la novela de formación nos ofrece un punto de partida inmejorable para la participación en el debate contemporáneo sobre la subjetividad humana. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>As a result, it is easy to discern how the parody embedded in both the Gothic and postmodernism could be trained at the *Bildungsroman* with its humanistic conception of subjectivity.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T193319Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T193319Z">
        <seg>En consecuencia, es fácil distinguir en qué medida la parodia incorporada en el gótico y en el posmodernismo podría guiar al Bildungsroman con su concepción humanista de la subjetividad.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>As for Lolita, there is no possibility of her bringing the relation close to the condition of marriage because she cannot even imagine the female role in marriage.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001025Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001025Z">
        <seg>En cuanto a Lolita, no hay posibilidad de que lleve la relación a una condición parecida a la de una unión conyugal, porque ni siquiera puede imaginar el rol femenino en el matrimonio.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>As for the translation of the word into English, although the “roman” in the word Bildungsroman means “novel,” “bildung” is more elusive and could be translated into English as “formation,” “development,” or “growth” (Graham 2).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T204419Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T204419Z">
        <seg>En cuanto a la traducción del término, aunque roman en Bildungsroman significa «novela», bildung es más difícil de precisar y podría traducirse al español como «formación», «desarrollo» o «crecimiento» (Graham 2).
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>As one of the greatest living American novelists, Cormac McCarthy is renowned for his daunting plunge into the darkest, scarcely plumbed recesses of the human mind and subjectivity, particularly when his writing is entangled with the Gothic with its unﬂinchingly visceral confrontation with the grossly material horrors of human existence.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T161447Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T161447Z">
        <seg>Como uno de los novelistas norteamericanos vivientes más importantes, Cormac McCarthy es reconocido por su zambullida abrumadora en los recovecos más oscuros y apenas conectados de la mente y la subjetividad humana, en especial, cuando su escritura está entrelazada con el estilo gótico, con el enfrentamiento visceral imperturbable, con los horrores materiales más repugnantes de la existencia humana. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>As soon as mutuality comes in, and common interests, and cooperation, and tolerance, and a concern for each other’s welfare or prestige in the world, the ethos of the family, of marriage, has asserted itself and they lose their status of lovers.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260402T224941Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260402T224941Z">
        <seg>En cuanto surge la reciprocidad, y los intereses comunes, y la cooperación, y la tolerancia, y la preocupación por el bienestar o el prestigio del otro en el mundo, se impone por sí mismo el ethos de la familia, del matrimonio, y pierden su condición de amantes.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>As stated above, the primary features of the Bildungsroman on which this study draws are those proposed by Dilthey.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T193535Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T193535Z">
        <seg>Según lo arriba expuesto, los rasgos principales del Bildungsroman, en los que se basa este estudio, son los propuestos por Dilthey. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>At least at the beginning of his love for *Lolita* there are no practical moral considerations, no practical personal considerations, that qualify H. H.’s behaviour.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260402T230011Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260402T230011Z">
        <seg>Al menos, al comienzo de su amor por Lolita no hay consideraciones morales ni personales prácticas que condicionen el comportamiento de H. H.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Ballard occupies the space between such binary oppositions as human/beast, male/female, and civilized/primitive.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T201045Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T201045Z">
        <seg>Ballard ocupa el espacio entre oposiciones binarias del tipo humano/ animal, masculino/ femenino y civilizado /primitivo.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>But</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T002315Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T002315Z">
        <seg>Pero </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>pensar partisan ≠ partidista</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>But Mr. Nabokov is not partisan to the point of being dishonest about the true nature of love.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Gabriel" changedate="20260407T170359Z" creationid="Gabriel" creationdate="20260407T170359Z">
        <seg>Pero el señor Nabokov no es partidista hasta el punto de ser deshonesto con respecto a la verdadera naturaleza del amor.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Hay un cambio de sujeto</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>But about love, which was once one of its chief preoccupations, it can tell us nothing at all.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T215510Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T215510Z">
        <seg>Pero sobre el amor, que una vez fue una de sus mayores preocupaciones, no se menciona nada en absoluto.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>De nuevo, hay que investigar nymph. Conc. exc.</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>But he is also a scholar of languages and he knows that *nymph* is the Greek word for bride.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184706Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184706Z">
        <seg>Pero es también un erudito de las lenguas, y sabe que nymph es la palabra griega para «novia». </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>fue inevitable que... Rever</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>But inevitably the sexual revolution of our time brought the relationship between marriage and passion-love to a virtual end.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221147Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221147Z">
        <seg>Pero fue inevitable que la revolución sexual de nuestro tiempo llevara a un final virtual la relación entre el matrimonio y el amor apasionado. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>allay ≠ disipar</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>But our doubts are allayed if the obsession can be accounted for by the known fact of a sexual peculiarity, an avowed aberration.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001553Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001553Z">
        <seg>Pero nuestras dudas se disipan si la obsesión puede explicarse por el hecho conocido de una peculiaridad sexual, una aberración confesada.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>By nefarious means Gothic villains usurp rightful heirs, rob reputable families of property and reputation while threatening the honour of their wives and orphaned daughters.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023243Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023243Z">
        <seg>Por medios nefarios, los villanos góticos usurpan a los herederos legítimos, despojan a familias respetables de su propiedad y reputación, al tiempo que amenazan el honor de sus esposas e hijas huérfanas. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Consequently, “humanistic historicism, conceived as an ideology of perfection through time” (Boes, 2012, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T183141Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T183141Z">
        <seg>En consecuencia, el «historicismo humanista, concebido como una ideología de perfeccionamiento a lo largo del tiempo» (Boes, 2012, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Cormac McCarthy’s *Child of God* as a postmodern Gothic parody of the Bildungsroman</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T154305Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T154305Z">
        <seg>El hijo de Dios, de Cormac McCarthy como parodia gótica posmoderna de la novela de formación</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Cormac McCarthy’s *Child of God* tackles the crisis of Man and its haunting horrors in a postmodern world of disorienting alienation and decentred subjectivity.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200319Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200319Z">
        <seg>El libro Hijo de Dios, de Cormac McCarthy, aborda la crisis del hombre y los horrores que lo acechan en un mundo posmoderno de alienación confusa y de subjetividad descentralizada. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Cormac McCarthy’s ﬁction has been widely acclaimed for its unstinting exploration of the subterranean recesses of human subjectivity and its inarticulate horrors.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T154744Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T154744Z">
        <seg>Las ficciones de Cormac McCarthy fueron considerablemente aclamadas debido a la incansable exploración que llevó a cabo acerca de los recovecos más profundos de la subjetividad humana y sus horrores indescriptibles. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Despite the distinct imbrication between *Child of God* and the Bildungsroman, a systematic study of its signiﬁcance vis-à-vis the novel’s stance on human subjectivity in postmodern times has not been conducted.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T154900Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T154900Z">
        <seg>. A pesar del ensamble marcado que existe entre El hijo de Dios y la novela de formación, aún no se llevó a cabo un estudio sistemático del significado de este ensamble frente a la postura que tiene la novela en cuanto a la subjetividad humana en tiempos posmodernos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Despite the lack of general consensus as to the speciﬁc deﬁnition of the term, its birth, as Sarah Graham points out, is “deeply implicated with the German Enlightenment” (2019, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T204027Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T204027Z">
        <seg>A pesar de la falta de consenso general en cuanto a la definición específica del término, su origen, tal como lo señala Sarah Graham, está «profundamente vinculado a la Ilustración alemana» (2019, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Dilthey’s insistence on the idea of formation is also in tune with Mikhail Bakhtin’s “process of becoming” (1986, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T204637Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T204637Z">
        <seg>La insistencia de Dilthey en el concepto de formación también se corresponde con el «proceso de devenir» de Mikhail Bakhtin (1986, p. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Do what, said Ballard.”</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T161253Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T161253Z">
        <seg>¿Hacer qué? Contestó Ballard”. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Enlightenment frustration with the relationship between res cogitans</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T182927Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T182927Z">
        <seg>la frustración ilustrada ante la relación entre la res cogitans</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Eric Hage is one of the very few scholars to point out the link between McCarthy’s novel and the Bildungsroman, but even his study gives it a passing mention.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T161715Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T161715Z">
        <seg>Eric Hage es uno de los pocos académicos que estableció la relación entre la novela de McCarthy y el género bildungsroman y, aun así, la mención fue efímera. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Exploiting the synergic relationship between the Gothic and postmodernism, the novel relies on the Gothic and its indelible association with the primitive, the barbaric, the tabooed, monstrosity, and horror in order to consummate the parodic representation.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200703Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200703Z">
        <seg>Al aprovechar esta relación sinérgica entre lo gótico y el posmodernismo, la novela se apoya en lo gótico y en su asociación indeleble con lo primitivo, lo bárbaro, lo tabú, la monstruosidad y el horror para consumar la representación paródica.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>pensar passion-love</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>For they assimilated it to marriage itself, and required of married love that it have the high brilliance and significance of passion-love.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221107Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221107Z">
        <seg>Por ende, lo incorporaron al propio matrimonio y exigieron que el amor conyugal tuviera el mismo esplendor y significado que el amor apasionado. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Furthermore, as it will be indicated, the postmodern Gothic nature of the novel undercuts any optimistic vision of the posthuman alternative in the wake of the dissolution of humanist subjectivity.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T203105Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203105Z">
        <seg>Además, como se indicará más adelante, la naturaleza gótica posmoderna de la novela socava cualquier visión optimista de la alternativa poshumana tras la disolución de la subjetividad humanista.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>G. B. Tennyson enumerates the ﬁve main characteristics Dilthey attributes to the Bildungsroman in the chapter entitled</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T193706Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T193706Z">
        <seg>G. B. Tennyson enumera las cinco características principales que Dilthey atribuye al Bildungsroman en el capítulo que se titula </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Gothic novels seem to sustain a nostalgic relish for a lost era of romance and adventure, for a world that, if barbaric, was, from the perspective of the late eighteenth century, also ordered.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023947Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023947Z">
        <seg>las novelas góticas parecen mantener un deleite nostálgico por una época perdida de romance y aventura, por un mundo que, aunque era bárbaro,  también era ordenado, desde la perspectiva de finales del siglo XVIII. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Gothic, too, was a term invoked in many political debates, signifying, for a range of political positions, revolutionary mobs, enlightened radicals and irrational adherence to tyrannical and superstitious feudal values.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023539Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023539Z">
        <seg>El término gótico también se empleaba en muchos debates políticos y, según diversas  posiciones políticas, podía referirse a las turbas revolucionarias, a los radicales ilustrados y a la adhesión irracional a valores feudales tiránicos y supersticiosos. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>H. eventually desires.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184627Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184627Z">
        <seg>H. acaba por desear.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>H.’s adoration of *Lolita*, and against the background of his sexual greed, whfch he calls “ape-like,” it comes over us as another reason for being shocked, that in recent fiction no lover has thought of his beloved with so much tenderness, that no woman has been so charmingly evoked, in such grace and delicacy, as Lolita; the description of her tennis game, in which even her racket has an erotic charm, is one of the few examples of rapture in modern writing.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T002140Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T002140Z">
        <seg>H. hacia Lolita, y contra el trasfondo de su codicia sexual, que él llama «simiesca», nos impacta como otro motivo para escandalizarnos, que en la ficción más reciente ningún amante ha pensado en su amada con tanta ternura, que ninguna mujer ha sido evocada de manera tan encantadora, con tanta gracia y delicadeza, como Lolita; la descripción de su juego de tenis, en la que incluso su raqueta tiene un encanto erótico, es uno de los pocos ejemplos de éxtasis en la literatura moderna.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>to be at pains ≠esmerarse.
No anteponer adjs.
ver Evoke
lust ≠ deseo</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>He does not impart this information to us, yet he is at pains, as I have remarked, to put us in mind of the rapturous, tortured marriage of Poe and Virginia, and one of his last meditations on *Lolita* is of the constancy she evokes from him despite the ravages of time having destroyed the old incitements to lust:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184715Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184715Z">
        <seg>No nos comunica este dato: sin embargo, se esmera —como ya he señalado— en ponernos en la senda del arrebatado y torturado matrimonio de Edgar Allan Poe y Virginia, y una de sus últimas meditaciones sobre Lolita versa sobre la constancia que ella le evoca, pese a que los estragos del tiempo han devastado los antiguos incentivos del deseo:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>He said.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T160616Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T160616Z">
        <seg>Preguntó él. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>He seeks companionship and ventures to ﬁnd it in a collection of posthuman beings, namely corpses, which reﬂect his own posthuman mode of existence.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T201127Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T201127Z">
        <seg>Busca compañía y se aventura a encontrarla en un grupo de seres poshumanos, en concreto cadáveres, que reflejan su propia forma de existencia poshumana. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Heaven s despite.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T002510Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T002510Z">
        <seg>en medio del cielo».
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Hence, a character in this kind of literature is both a component and a topic of the work of art” (Bates, 2009, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T183246Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T183246Z">
        <seg>Por consiguiente, un personaje en este tipo de literatura es a la vez componente y objeto de la obra de arte» (Bates, 2009, p. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>His third novel, *Child of God* (1973), achieves the foregoing by tapping into Gothic and postmodern features, both of which demonstrate a corresponding concern with human subjectivity.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T154800Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T154800Z">
        <seg>El hijo de Dios (1973), que fue su tercera novela, logra lo antedicho mediante la utilización de las características góticas y posmodernas, las cuales manifiestan un interés propio de la subjetividad humana.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>However, the uniqueness of the protagonist has culturally representative overtones, which will be further analysed in the postmodern Gothic context of the novel.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T194155Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T194155Z">
        <seg>Sin embargo, la singularidad del protagonista presenta matices culturalmente representativos, que serán analizados más a fondo en el contexto gótico posmoderno de la novela.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>I am not sure just how I respond to the moral implication of this passage—I am not sure that with it, as with other passages in which H. H.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Gabriel" changedate="20260407T182157Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185044Z">
        <seg>No estoy seguro de cómo responder a la implicación moral de este fragmento; no estoy seguro de que, en él —como en otros en que H. H. habla de la profunda y la salvaje solemnidad de su amor y su remordimiento—, el Señor Vladimir Nabokov no haya tendido una trampa emocional al lector; que acaso las últimas intensidades de H. H. no debieran recibirse con bastante más ironía de la que en un primer momento parecen reclamar.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>no anteponer adjs.</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>I am not sure just how I respond to the moral implication of this passage—I am not sure that with it, as with other passages in which H. H. speaks of the depth and wild solemnity of his love and remorse, Mr. Nabokov has not laid an emotional trap for the reader, that perhaps H. H.’s last intensities ought not to be received with considerably more irony than at first they call for.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Gabriel" changedate="20260407T182422Z" creationid="Gabriel" creationdate="20260407T182422Z">
        <seg>No estoy seguro de cómo responder a la implicación moral de este fragmento; no estoy seguro de que, en él —como en otros en que H. H. habla de la profunda y la salvaje solemnidad de su amor y su remordimiento—, el Señor Vladimir Nabokov no haya tendido una trampa emocional al lector; que acaso las últimas intensidades de H. H. no debieran recibirse con bastante más ironía de la que en un primer momento parecen reclamar.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Tenemos primo hermano en español</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>I can, I think, manage to take seriously a tragic Humbert, but I find myself easier with Humbert the anti-hero, with Humbert as cousin-german to Rameau’s nephew.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T185144Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185144Z">
        <seg>Creo que puedo tomarme seriamente a un Humbert trágico, pero me hallo más con el Humbert antihéroe, como primo del sobrino de Rameau.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>I don’t say this with the least certitude.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T185111Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185111Z">
        <seg>No afirmo esto con la menor de las certezas.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>I don’t want to put my uneasiness with the tragic Humbert as an objection.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T185158Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185158Z">
        <seg>No quiero presentar mi incomodidad ante el Humbert trágico como una objeción.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>passion-love al glosario
Invertir S y P.</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>I have represented passion-love as being the antithesis of marriage and as coming to an end when the conditions characteristic of marriage impose themselves, by whatever means, upon the lovers.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184523Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184523Z">
        <seg>He presentado el amor-pasión como la antítesis del matrimonio y como algo que toca a su fin cuando las condiciones propias del matrimonio se imponen, por los medios que fueren, sobre los amantes. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>castaña rojiza y almendrada. se aleja de la descripción de un cabello.</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>I insist the world know how much I loved my Lolita, *this* Lolita, pale and polluted, and big with another’s child, but still grey-eyed, still sooty-lashed, still auburn and almond.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184922Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184922Z">
        <seg>Insisto en que el mundo sepa cuánto amé a mi Lolita, a esta Lolita, pálida y mancillada, preñada del hijo de otro, pero aún de ojos grises, aún de pestañas tiznadas, aún castaña rojiza y almendrada. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>ver grados "stupid vs estúpido"

account ≠ relato</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>I later regretted having been cross at their stupidity when I found myself doubting the verisimilitude of Proust’s account of the relation of Swann to Odette.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001508Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001508Z">
        <seg>Más tarde, lamenté haberme molestado por su estupidez, cuando me encontré dudando de la verosimilitud del relato de Proust sobre la relación entre Swann y Odette.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>comparar Mr. y Señor</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>I may seem to have been talking about *Lolita* as if in writing it Mr. Nabokov had undertaken a job of emotional archaeology.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001657Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001657Z">
        <seg>Puede parecer que he estado hablando de Lolita, como si al escribirla, el señor Nabokov hubiera emprendido una labor de arqueología emocional.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Foco --&gt; sentido</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>If one can rely on the evidence of fiction to discover the modern idea of the right relation between a man and a woman, it would probably begin with a sexual meeting, more or less tentative or experimental, and go on to sexual communion, after which marriage would take place.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221259Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221259Z">
        <seg>Si una persona se basara en la ficción para descubrir el concepto moderno de la relación correcta entre un hombre y una mujer, sería probable que iniciara con un encuentro sexual, un tanto tentativo o experimental, seguido de la comunión sexual, luego de lo cual llegaría el matrimonio.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>¿Podés usar gerundio?</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>If our fiction gives accurate testimony, love has disappeared from the Western world, just as Denis de Rougemont said it should.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T215415Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T215415Z">
        <seg>Si nuestra ficción nos da un testimonio preciso, podemos aseverar que el amor desapareció del mundo occidental, tal como vaticinó Denis de Rougemont. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Illegitimate power and violence is not only put on display but threatens to consume the world of civilised and domestic values.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023307Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023307Z">
        <seg>El poder ilegítimo y la violencia no solo se exhiben, sino que amenazan con extinguir del mundo los valores de la vida civilizada y familiar. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In *Cormac McCarthy:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T161736Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T161736Z">
        <seg>En el libro Cormac McCarthy:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In a more specific historical sense, Gothic was associated with the history of the northern, Germanic nations whose fierce avowal of the values of freedom and democracy was claimed as an ancient heritage.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023602Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023602Z">
        <seg>En un sentido histórico más específico, el gótico se asociaba con la historia de las naciones germánicas del norte, que reivindicaron su antiguo legado a través de una enérgica afirmación de los valores de libertad y democracia.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In a similar vein, Stanley Bates argues that the formation of the *Bildungsroman* somehow “conﬁrm[s] Hegel’s view that a central line of literature will concern the formation and development of individual consciousness in a variety of contingent circumstances.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T183230Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T183230Z">
        <seg>En una línea similar, Stanley Bates sostiene que la formación del Bildungsroman de algún modo «confirma[n] la perspectiva de Hegel según la cual una línea central de la literatura se ocupará de la formación y el desarrollo de la conciencia individual en una variedad de circunstancias contingentes.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In fact, as David Punter and Glennis Byron note,</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T174917Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T174917Z">
        <seg>De hecho, así lo señalan David Punter y Glennis Byron:
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In nineteenth-century Gothic fiction the trappings of aristocracy, the castles and counts, give way to narratives whose action centres on urban, domestic, commercial and professional figures and locales.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T024459Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T024459Z">
        <seg>En la ficción gótica del siglo XIX, los símbolos de la aristocracia, los castillos y los condes, dan paso a narraciones cuya acción se centra en figuras y espacios urbanos, domésticos, comerciales y profesionales. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In order to establish a link between *Child of God* and the tradition of the *Bildungsroman*, an examination of the characteristics of the Bildungsroman and their compatibility with the novel would be vital.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T193506Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T193506Z">
        <seg>Para establecer un vínculo entre Hijo de Dios y la tradición del Bildungsroman, resulta fundamental examinar las características del Bildungsroman y su compatibilidad con la novela. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In particular, *Child of God* addresses the crisis of Man by establishing a speciﬁc line of communication with the Bildungsroman through postmodern parody in such a way as to both partake in and critique the tradition’s humanist ideals.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200453Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200453Z">
        <seg>En particular, Hijo de Dios aborda la crisis del hombre y establece una línea específica de comunicación con el Bildungsroman mediante la parodia posmoderna, y lo hace de tal manera, que participa y a la vez critica los ideales humanistas de la tradición del Bildungsroman. 
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In particular, the Cartesian subjectivity enmeshed in the Enlightenment discourse, which Charles Taylor regards as an “epistemological revolution with anthropological consequences” (1977, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T191348Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T191348Z">
        <seg>En particular, la subjetividad cartesiana imbricada en el discurso ilustrado, que Charles Taylor considera una «revolución epistemológica con consecuencias antropológicas» (1977, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In particular, the current paper argues that *Child of God* is a postmodern parody—in accordance with Linda Hutcheon’s deﬁnition—of the Bildungsroman, which draws on subversive Gothic elements in order to make a polemic statement about the status of Man in the postmodern world.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T160350Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T160350Z">
        <seg>En concreto, en este artículo se aduce que El hijo de Dios es una parodia posmoderna (de acuerdo con la definición de Linda Hutcheon) de la novela de formación, que se basa en los elementos góticos subversivos con el propósito de efectuar una declaración polémica acerca del estatus del “hombre” en el mundo posmoderno. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In particular, the setting and characterization are the two vital components that enact and mirror the theme and plot in the Bildungsroman.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200801Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200801Z">
        <seg>En particular, el escenario y la caracterización son los dos componentes fundamentales que representan y reflejan el tema y la trama en el Bildungsroman.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In the *mutuality* and *warmth of their *togetherness* their children are included.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221414Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221414Z">
        <seg>En la “reciprocidad” y “la calidez de la unión” se incluye a los hijos. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In the figures and settings that dominate Gothic narratives this ambivalence is manifested in terms of the genre’s affiliations with class.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023819Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023819Z">
        <seg>En las siluetas y en los escenarios que dominan las narraciones góticas, esta ambivalencia se manifiesta en términos de las relaciones del género con la clase. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In the skeletons that leap from family closets and the erotic and often incestuous tendencies of Gothic villains there emerges the awful spectre of complete social disintegration in which virtue cedes to vice, reason to desire, law to tyranny.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023346Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023346Z">
        <seg>En los esqueletos que saltan de los armarios familiares y en las tendencias eróticas y a menudo incestuosas de los villanos góticos, emerge el espantoso espectro de una completa desintegración social en la que la virtud cede al vicio, la razón al deseo y la ley a la tiranía.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>In this respect Gothic fiction preserves older traditions rather than attacking the aristocratic legacy of feudalism.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T024006Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T024006Z">
        <seg>En este sentido, la ficción gótica preserva tradiciones más antiguas en lugar de atacar el legado aristocrático del feudalismo. 

</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>su ambigüedad de intención: mejorar, y rever los dos puntos</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Indeed, for me one of the attractions of *Lolita* is its ambiguity of tone—which is pretty well exemplified in the passage I have quoted—and its ambiguity of intention, its ability to arouse uneasiness, to throw the reader off balance, to require him to change his stance and shift his position and move on.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T185208Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185208Z">
        <seg>De hecho, para mí, uno de los grandes atractivos de Lolita reside en su tono ambiguo —bien ejemplificada en el fragmento citado— y en su ambigüedad de intención: su capacidad de suscitar desasosiego, de descolocar al lector, de obligarlo a mudar de postura, a desplazarse, a proseguir. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Introduction</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T160545Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T160545Z">
        <seg>Introducción </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>No unir oraciones</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It enables husband and wife to *build a life together.*</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221346Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221346Z">
        <seg>que les permiten al marido y a la mujer “construir una vida juntos”.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It has been commonly acknowledged that Johann Wolfgang von Goethe’s *Wilhelm Meister’s Apprenticeship* (1795) is the “paradigmatic example” of the German *Bildungsroman* or the novel of formation (Boes, 2012, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T203835Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203835Z">
        <seg>Se reconoce, por lo general, que Los años de aprendizaje de Wilhelm Meister (1795) de Johann Wolfgang von Goethe es el «ejemplo paradigmático» del Bildungsroman alemán o novela de formación (Boes, 2012, p. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It is</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T183027Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T183027Z">
        <seg>Es la</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>¿Qué vamos a hacer con citas como esta?</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It is H. H., that mixture of ferocity and jocularity, who reminds us that “Love seeketh only self to please...</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T002358Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T002358Z">
        <seg>H. H. es, con esa mezcla de ferocidad y jocosidad, quien nos recuerda que «El amor solo busca complacerse a sí mismo…
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>about</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It is about love.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T215228Z">
        <seg>Trata sobre el amor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It may be that Mr. Nabokov really wants us to believe with entire seriousness that we are witnessing the culmination of H. H.’s moral evolution.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T185123Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185123Z">
        <seg>Puede ser que el Señor Nabokov realmente quiera que creamos, con plena seriedad, que estamos asistiendo a la culminación de la evolución moral de H. H.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It need not be stated that this study also rebuts the claim made by a number of scholars that the novel formation is “primarily a nineteenth-century phenomenon” (Boes,</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T190707Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T190707Z">
        <seg>No es necesario señalar que el presente estudio refuta asimismo la tesis sostenida por diversos especialistas, según la cual la formación de la novela constituiría «primordialmente un fenómeno del Siglo XIX» (Boes, </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Usar cursivas</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It seems to me that it is impossible to miss the parti pris in Mr. Nabokov’s archaeological undertaking, the impulse to mock and discredit all forms of progressive rationalism not only because they are stupid in themselves but because they have brought the madness of love to an end.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T002212Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T002212Z">
        <seg>Me parece que es imposible pasar por alto el parti pris en la tarea arqueológica del señor Nabokov, el impulso de burlarse y desacreditar todas las formas de racionalismo progresista, no solo porque son estúpidas en sí mismas, sino porque han puesto fin a la locura del amor.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It was not a relation of the heart and the inclination, and the situation of the lady made it impossible for her to give herself in free will because it was expected that she give herself in obedience.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T220650Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T220650Z">
        <seg>No era una relación del corazón y de la voluntad, y la situación en la que se encontraba la mujer le impedía entregarse por voluntad propia, ya que se esperaba que lo hiciera por obediencia. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>concordancia. Redacción. Connotación lover</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It was surely one of the most interesting and important of cultural revisions when the middle classes, which had been quite specifically excluded from the pleasure and dignity of love (one cannot be both busy and a lover), began to appropriate the prestige of this mode of feeling and to change it in the process of adopting it.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221036Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221036Z">
        <seg>Sin duda, uno de los cambios culturales más interesantes y significativos se dio cuando la clase media, la cual había sido excluida expresamente del placer y la dignidad del amor (una persona no puede estar ocupada y ser amante al mismo tiempo), empezó a apropiarse del prestigio de esta manera de sentir y a cambiarlo al adoptarlo. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>sentido</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It was the convention for him to say that he was sick and to make a show of his physical and mental derangement.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221607Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221607Z">
        <seg>Tenía la costumbre de decir que estaba enfermo y hacer alarde de su trastorno físico y mental.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It will be demonstrated that the novel reiterates the elements of the Bildungsroman with ironic critical distance, portraying the horrid dissolution of humanist subjectivity rather than its teleological progress toward positive identity formation and social integration.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T160525Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T160525Z">
        <seg>Se demostrará que la novela retoma los elementos del género bildungsroman con una distancia irónica crítica, tras representar la horrorosa disolución de la subjetividad humanista antes que su progreso teleológico hacia la formación positiva de la identidad y la integración social.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>It will be indicated, however, that although the protagonist edges toward posthuman monstrosity in such a way as to limn the failure of the Bildungsroman and its humanist tradition, the posthuman liminality and marginality ensuing from this disintegration are not celebrated in the novel, as its Gothicity serves to voice the consequent horrors of this dissolution.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T160537Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T160537Z">
        <seg>Cabe señalar que, sin embargo, aunque el protagonista se acerca a la monstruosidad poshumana de manera que pone de manifiesto la falla de la novela de formación y su tradición humanista, la liminalidad y la marginalidad poshumanas que derivan de esta desintegración no se ponderan en esta novela, así como su goticidad ayuda a revelar los horrores de esta disolución. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Jean Francois Lyotard also points out the intimate relationship between Cartesian philosophy and the Bildungsroman when he notes that in Descartes the legitimacy of science is demonstrated “in a *Bildungsroman*, which is what the *Discourse on Method* amounts to” (1984, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T204321Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T204321Z">
        <seg>Jean-François Lyotard también destaca la estrecha relación entre la filosofía cartesiana y el Bildungsroman al señalar que en Descartes la legitimidad de la ciencia se demuestra «en un Bildungsroman, que es en lo que consiste el Discurso del método» (1984, p. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Lastly, by tracing the protagonist’s ironically degenerative process of becoming a posthuman monster, which is represented through contributive Gothic elements deployed in the setting and characterization of the novel, it will be shown that *Child of God* is a postmodern parody of the humanist tradition of the Bildungsroman.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T203028Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203028Z">
        <seg>Por último, al rastrear el proceso irónicamente degenerativo del protagonista en su transformación en un monstruo poshumano, que se representa mediante elementos góticos que contribuyen a la utilización del escenario y a la caracterización de la novela, se demostrará que Hijo de Dios es una parodia posmoderna de la tradición humanista de la novela de formación o Bildungsroman.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Lionel Trilling</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="borrar" changedate="20260402T144713Z" creationid="borrar" creationdate="20260402T144713Z">
        <seg>Lionel Trilling</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>rever settle and sink roots.</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Lolita gives us no chance to settle and sink roots.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T185216Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185216Z">
        <seg>Lolita no nos concede reposo ni arraigo. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>puntuación</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Lolita is not about sex, but about love.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T215152Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T215152Z">
        <seg>Lolita no trata sobre el sexo sino sobre el amor. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Maryam Soltan Beyad ^1 &amp; Zohreh Ramin ^1</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T154713Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T154713Z">
        <seg>Maryam Soltan Beyad y Zohreh Ramin</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>McCarthy presents one of his most morbid explorations of human degradation and monstrosity in his third novel, *Child of God* (1973).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T161503Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T161503Z">
        <seg>McCarthy expone una de sus exploraciones más morbosas sobre la degradación y la monstruosidad humanas en su tercera novela, El hijo de Dios (1973). </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Mona Jafari ^1:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T154320Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T154320Z">
        <seg>Mona Jafari</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Moving from real and toy animals to posthuman corpses, the non-human community escalates in a way that echoes Ballard’s progressive alienation and dehumanization.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T201246Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T201246Z">
        <seg>Al pasar de animales reales y de juguete a cadáveres poshumanos, la comunidad no humana se expande de manera tal que refleja la alienación y la deshumanización progresivas de Ballard. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Mr. Nabokov is not partisan to the point of being dishonest about the true nature of love.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T002327Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T002327Z">
        <seg>el señor Nabokov no es partidista hasta el punto de ser deshonesto con respecto a la verdadera naturaleza del amor.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Pensar y acordar "mister".
Nymph es un error.
reader of fiction</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Mr. Nabokov is, among his other accomplishments, an eminent entomologist and I shall leave it to some really rigorous close reader of fiction to tell us what an entomological novelist wants us to do with the fact that *nymph* is the name for the young of an insect without complete metamorphosis.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184649Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184649Z">
        <seg>El Señor Vladimir Nabokov es, entre otras cosas, un eminente entomólogo, y dejaré a algún lector verdaderamente riguroso la tarea de decirnos qué pretende un novelista entomólogo que hagamos con el hecho de que nymph sea el nombre que recibe la fase juvenil de un insecto sin metamorfosis completa. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>reg. preposicional.

Cuando hay estos cortes, por favor avisame y lo resuelvo</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>My having mentioned Denis de Rougemont and his curious, belated, supererogatory onslaught on love will indicate that I have in mind what I</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T220446Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T220446Z">
        <seg>El haber mencionado a Denis de Rougemont y su embestida curiosa, tardía y superflua al amor denota que tengo en mente lo que   </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Cuando hay cortes, avisame y lo arreglo. Ahora ya está arreglado.
Hay un sujeto superfluo.
Se puede invertir S y P.</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>My having mentioned Denis de Rougemont and his curious, belated, supererogatory onslaught on love will indicate that I have in mind what I seem to remember he calls passion-love, a kind of love with which European literature has dealt since time immemorial but with especial intensity since the Arthurian romances and the code of courtly love.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Gabriel" changedate="20260407T145508Z" creationid="Gabriel" creationdate="20260407T145508Z">
        <seg>El haber mencionado a Denis de Rougemont y su embestida curiosa, tardía y superflua al amor denota que tengo en mente lo que creo recordar que él llama amor pasional, una clase de amor con el que la literatura europea tuvo que lidiar desde siempre, pero con una intensidad especial desde los romances artúricos y el código del amor cortesano.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Nevertheless, as Petru Golban notes, the “novel of development” and the “novel of formation” are the most frequently used English equivalents of the Bildungsroman (2018, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T204513Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T204513Z">
        <seg> No obstante, como señala Petru Golban, «novela de desarrollo» y «novela de formación» son los equivalentes más utilizados de Bildungsroman (2018, p. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Nevertheless, it bears noting that the Gothic is not a mere ﬁctional reﬂection but, rather, a forerunner in the struggle to tackle the growing horror of</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T174355Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T174355Z">
        <seg>No obstante, cabe señalar que lo gótico no es un mero reflejo ficcional, sino más bien un precursor en la lucha por encarar el creciente horror de </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Nevertheless, it was with Wilhelm Dilthey’s 1870 biography of Friedrich Schleiermacher and his</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T203559Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203559Z">
        <seg>No obstante, el término adquirió relevancia en la crítica moderna con la biografía de Friedrich Schleiermacher escrita por Wilhelm Dilthey en 1870 y con su </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Now that a synergic relationship between the Gothic and postmodernism has been established through their mutual engagement with terror, human subjectivity, and parody, these elements and their function can be examined in McCarthy’s *Child of God*, which this study considers a postmodern Gothic novel that makes a statement about the present through a parodic reappropriation of the humanist *Bildungsroman*.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T193425Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T193425Z">
        <seg>Ahora que se ha establecido una relación sinérgica entre el gótico y el posmodernismo a través de su compromiso mutuo con el terror, la subjetividad humana y la parodia, es posible examinar estos elementos y su función en Hijo de Dios de McCarthy, obra que este estudio considera una novela gótica posmoderna que formula una reflexión sobre el presente mediante una reapropiación paródica del Bildungsroman humanista.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>dependían</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Nowadays we find it difficult to give credence to the idea that a man might feel that his reason and his very life depended on the response to him of a particular woman.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001153Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001153Z">
        <seg>Hoy en día, nos resulta difícil dar crédito a la idea de que un hombre pudiera sentir que su razón y su propia vida dependían de la respuesta que le diera una mujer en particular.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>concordancia de sujeto en gerundio</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Nowadays we use the word chiefly to mean an intense feeling, forgetting the old distinction between a passion and an emotion, the former being an emotion before which we are helpless, which we have to *suffer*, in whose grip we are *passive.*</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221546Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221546Z">
        <seg>En la actualidad, esta palabra se usa, sobre todo, para hablar de un sentimiento intenso, dejando de lado la antigua distinción que se hacía entre pasión y emoción, la primera es una emoción ante la que somos indefensos, por la que tenemos que “sufrir”, en cuya sujeción somos “pasivos”.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Old castles, knights and malevolent aristocrats seem to fit into an enlightenment pattern identifying all things Gothic with the tyranny and barbarity of feudal times.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023844Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023844Z">
        <seg>Los castillos antiguos, los caballeros y los aristócratas malévolos parecen encajar en un modelo ilustrado que identifica el gótico en su totalidad con la tiranía y la barbarie de los tiempos feudales. 
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Opposed to all forms of tyranny and slavery, the warlike, Gothic tribes of northern Europe were popularly believed to have brought down the Roman empire.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023648Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023648Z">
        <seg>Las tribus guerreras góticas del norte de Europa, que se oponian a todas las formas de tiranía y esclavitud, fueron las que, según la creencia popular, derribaron el Imperio romano.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>prep.</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Passion-love was a mode of feeling not available to everyone—the authorities on the subject restricted it to the aristocracy—but it was always of the greatest interest to almost everyone who was at all interested in the feelings, and it had a continuing influence on other kinds of love and on the literary conventions through which love was represented.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T220518Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T220518Z">
        <seg>El amor pasional era una manera de sentir que no estaba al alcance de todos (las autoridades en el tema lo restringían a la aristocracia), pero siempre fue de gran interés para casi cualquiera que estuviera interesado en los sentimientos, y tuvo una influencia continua en otros tipos de amor y sobre convenciones literarias que representaban el amor.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Pathology naturalises the strange particularity of the lover’s preference.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001616Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001616Z">
        <seg>La patología naturaliza la extraña singularidad de la preferencia del amante.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Perhaps I shall be better understood if I put the statement in this form:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T215130Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T215130Z">
        <seg>Tal vez me van a entender mejor si expreso el enunciado de la siguiente manera:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Perhaps all that the two now have in common is the belief that the lovers must freely choose each other and that their choice has the highest sanctions and must not be interfered with.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221215Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221215Z">
        <seg>Tal vez lo que ambos hoy tienen en común es la convicción de que los amantes deben elegirse con libertad, y de que esa elección tiene gran aceptación y no debe ser objeto de intromisión.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>—sobre el mar—: mejorar.
Aclarar la redacción
lovely ≠ amada</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Perhaps he even wants us to believe that his ascent from “ape-like” lust to a love which challenges the devils below and the angels up over the sea to ever dissever his soul from the soul of the lovely Annabel Lee constitutes the life cycle of the erotic instinct.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T185134Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185134Z">
        <seg>Quizá, incluso, quiera que creamos que su ascenso desde una lujuria «simiesca» hacia un amor que desafía a los demonios de abajo y a los ángeles de arriba —sobre el mar— a separar su alma del alma de la amada Annabel Lee constituye el ciclo vital del instinto erótico. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Perhaps it is the curious moral mobility it urges on us that accounts for its remarkable ability to represent certain aspects of American life.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T185227Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185227Z">
        <seg>Tal vez sea esa peculiar movilidad moral que nos impone lo que explique su extraordinaria aptitud para representar ciertos aspectos de la vida estadounidense. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>No agregar espacios al final</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Probably nothing.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184656Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184656Z">
        <seg>Probablemente nada. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Rather than approximate the ideal Man, the protagonist becomes a posthuman monster, who, as the harbinger of category crisis, threatens the very essence of human subjectivity.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T201017Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T201017Z">
        <seg>En lugar de aproximarse al hombre ideal, el protagonista se convierte en un monstruo poshumano quien, como heraldo de una crisis de categoría, amenaza la propia esencia de la subjetividad humana. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Rational distancing and disavowal of past forms of power, however, is belied by the continued fascination with the architecture, customs and values of the Middle Ages:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023910Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023910Z">
        <seg>Sin embargo, el distanciamiento racional y el rechazo de las formas pasadas de poder quedan ocultos frente a la fascinación persistente por la arquitectura, las costumbres y los valores de la Edad Media:
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Recently I read</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001227Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001227Z">
        <seg>Hace poco, leí </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>ver "graduate"</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Recently I read *Liber Amoris* with some graduate students and found that they had no understanding whatever of Hazlitt’s obsessive commitment to Sarah Walker.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Gabriel" changedate="20260407T163909Z" creationid="Gabriel" creationdate="20260407T163909Z">
        <seg>Hace poco leí *Liber Amoris* con algunos estudiantes de posgrado y comprobé que no tenían la más mínima comprensión del compromiso obsesivo de Hazlitt hacia Sarah Walker.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Roman tyranny was subsequently identified with the Catholic Church, and the production of Gothic novels in northern European Protestant countries often had an anti-Catholic subtext.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023712Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023712Z">
        <seg>Con posterioridad, la tiranía romana se identificó con la Iglesia católica, y la producción de novelas góticas en países protestantes del norte de Europa solía tener, a menudo, un trasfondo anticatólico.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Save for the German origin of the term *Bildungsroman*, virtually every other aspect of the genre has been open to debate.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T203210Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203210Z">
        <seg>Salvo por el origen alemán del término Bildungsroman, prácticamente todos los demás aspectos del género han sido objeto de debate.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Evitar "De manera", salvo que sea 'de manera'.
No anteponer adjs.
Espacio en H. H.
rever "le niega..."

ver "sea"</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>She remains perpetually the cruel mistress; even after her lover has won physical possession of her, she withholds the favour of her feeling, for she has none to give, by reason of her age, possibly by reason of her temperament.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001100Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001100Z">
        <seg>De manera perpetua, permanece en el papel de la cruel amante; incluso después de que H.H. haya conseguido poseerla físicamente, ella le niega acceso a su sentimiento, pues no tiene ninguno que dar, debido a su edad, y es posible que también sea por su temperamento.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Muy buena traducción, salvo seca y crujiente</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>She was only the faint violet whiff and dead leaf echo of the nymphet I had rolled myself upon with such cries in the past; an echo on the brink of a russet ravine, with a far wood under a white sky, and brown leaves choking the brook and one last cricket in the crisp weeds...</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184818Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184818Z">
        <seg>Ella no era sino el tenue efluvio violáceo y el eco de hoja muerta de la nínfula sobre la cual me había arrojado con tales clamores en el pasado; un eco al borde de un barranco rojizo, con un bosque remoto bajo un cielo blanco, y hojas pardas sofocando el arroyo y un último grillo entre la maleza seca y crujiente... </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Sheehan further argues that If Cartesian individualism gave to the novel a model of subjectivity, Cartesian dualism provided the dilemma that</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T182835Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T182835Z">
        <seg>Sheehan sostiene además que, si el individualismo cartesiano proporcionó a la novela un modelo de subjetividad, el dualismo cartesiano planteó el dilema que</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Similarly, McCarthy’s *Child of God* depicts the conﬂict-plagued life and identity formation of a single character, that is, a young man named Lester Ballard.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T193929Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T193929Z">
        <seg>De manera similar, el libro Hijo de Dios, de McCarthy, describe la vida plagada de conflictos y la formación de la identidad de un solo personaje, es decir, un joven llamado Lester Ballard. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Similarly, the Gothic cogs in *Child of God*’s machine of postmodern parody operate primarily in the setting and the characterization of the protagonist, who follows a path toward posthuman subjectivity, which the novel equates with monstrosity.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200828Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200828Z">
        <seg>De manera similar, los engranajes góticos en la maquinaria de la parodia posmoderna de Hijo de Dios operan principalmente en el escenario y en la caracterización del protagonista, quien sigue un camino hacia una subjetividad poshumana que la novela equipara con la monstruosidad. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Similarly, the Gothic lineaments in characterization undercut the teleology of individuality that informs the Bildungsroman.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200948Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200948Z">
        <seg>De manera similar, los rasgos góticos en la caracterización socavan la teleología de la individualidad que fundamenta el Bildungsroman. 
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Since one of the paradigmatic literary incarnations of the discourse of humanism is the *Bildungsroman*, it provides the novel with an apt target in the postmodern debate about the condition of human subjectivity.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200410Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200410Z">
        <seg>El Bildungsroman es una de las encarnaciones literarias paradigmáticas del discurso del humanismo, y proporciona a la novela un objetivo apropiado en el debate posmoderno sobre la condición de la subjetividad humana. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>So that a man in the grip of an obsessional lust and a girl of twelve make the ideal couple for a story about love written in our time.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260402T225939Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260402T225939Z">
        <seg>De modo que un hombre dominado por una lujuria obsesiva y una niña de doce años forman la pareja ideal para una historia de amor escrita en nuestro tiempo.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Invertir</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Something of that expectation still persists—it is still the love poetry and the love music and the love dramas of passionlove in its later forms that shape our notions of what the erotic experience can be in intensity, in variety, in grace.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221128Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221128Z">
        <seg>Algo de esa expectativa aún persiste: siguen siendo los poemas de amor y la música romántica y los dramas amorosos del amor apasionado en sus versiones posteriores los que moldean nuestras nociones de lo que puede ser la experiencia erótica en cuanto a intensidad, variedad y elegancia.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Subsequent to the introduction of Hutcheon’s deﬁnition of postmodern parody, the apt imbrication between parody, the Gothic, and postmodernism—with particular emphasis on the question of subjectivity—and its relevance to the novel are discussed.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T203001Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203001Z">
        <seg>Trás la introducción de la definición de parodia posmoderna de Hutcheon, se analiza la conexión pertinente entre la parodia, el gótico y el posmodernismo, con especial énfasis en la cuestión de la subjetividad, y su relevancia para la novela. 
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>TRANSGRESSION</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T024537Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T024537Z">
        <seg>TRANSGRESIÓN
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>concordancia, referencia.
ethos iría en cursiva. La manera de indicarlo es con asteriscos: *ethos*</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>That is, their behaviour to each other must not be touched by practicality, their virtues must not be of a kind that acknowledges the claims of the world.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260402T224901Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260402T224901Z">
        <seg>Es decir, el comportamiento para con el otro no debe regirse por consideraciones prácticas, sus virtudes no deben dar cabida a las exigencias del mundo.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>invertir S y P. Redcción. Aspecto</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>That the possibility of love could exist only apart from and more or less in opposition to marriage has been, by and large, the traditional supposition of the European upper classes, which have placed most of their expectations of erotic pleasure outside of marriage.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T220720Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T220720Z">
        <seg>El hecho de que la posibilidad de amar existiera solo fuera del matrimonio y casi opuesto a él fue, en general, la suposición tradicional de las clases altas europeas, quienes pusieron gran parte de sus expectativas sobre el placer erótico fuera del matrimonio.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The Cartesian subject with its mind/body dualism is predicated on three notions vis-à-vis the subject’s relation to knowledge and the external world, that is to say, the “self-deﬁning, all-knowing, and formally empowered subject of consciousness” comprises the Cartesian subject of humanism (Gandhi, 1998, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T191413Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T191413Z">
        <seg>El sujeto cartesiano, con su dualismo mente/cuerpo, se funda en tres nociones en lo que respecta a la relación del sujeto con el conocimiento y el mundo exterior; a saber, el «sujeto de la conciencia autodeterminante, omnisciente y formalmente investido de facultades» constituye el sujeto cartesiano del humanismo (Gandhi, 1998, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The Frankenstein-like isolation and claustrophobic focus on Ballard highlight the individualism and the concern with individual identity formation in the novel.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T194125Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T194125Z">
        <seg>El aislamiento de tipo frankensteiniano y el enfoque claustrofóbico en Ballard pone de manifiesto el individualismo y la preocupación por la formación de la identidad individual en la novela. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Segmento traducido como muestra</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The Last Lover:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="borrar" changedate="20260402T145744Z">
        <seg>El último amante:</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The anxieties about the past and its forms of power are projected on to malevolent and villainous aristocrats in order to consolidate the ascendancy of middle-class values.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T024240Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T024240Z">
        <seg>Las ansiedades sobre el pasado y las formas de poder se proyectan en aristócratas malévolos y villanos con el fin de consolidar el ascenso de los valores de la clase media. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The association with Enlightenment humanism has been noted by Dilthey, who posits that the Bildungsroman is “an aesthetic expression of the Enlightenment concept of *Bildung* and… presents a regulated development of the hero or heroine who has to reach fulﬁllment and harmony by passing through various conﬂicts of life” (Golban 10).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T204144Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T204144Z">
        <seg>Dilthey ha notado esta asociación con el humanismo ilustrado, y sostiene que el Bildungsroman es «una expresión estética del concepto de Ilustración de Bildung y presenta un desarrollo mesurado del héroe o de la heroína que ha de alcanzar la plenitud y la armonía al atravesar diversos conflictos en la vida» (Golban 10). 
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>al de ...

redacción</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The condition towards which such a marriage aspires is *health*—a marriage is praised by being called a *healthy* marriage.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221458Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221458Z">
        <seg>El estado al que un matrimonio de este tipo aspira es al de la “salud”: un matrimonio es reconocido cuando lo consideran “saludable”,  </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Ver roles temáticos de narrar</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The contemporary novel can tell us about sex, and about sexual communion, and about mutuality, and about the strong fine relationships that grow up between men and women; and it can tell us about marriage.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T215448Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T215448Z">
        <seg>La novela contemporánea narra acerca del sexo, y también de la comunión sexual, y de la reciprocidad, y de las relaciones sólidas y estrechas que se forjan entre hombres y mujeres; y narra acerca del matrimonio. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The decade of the French Revolution was also the period when the Gothic novel was at its most popular.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023509Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023509Z">
        <seg>La década de la Revolución Francesa fue también el período en el que la novela gótica alcanzó su mayor popularidad.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The distortion of perspective which is a constant hallmark of Gothic ﬁction ﬁnds a further ‘home’ in the postmodern, and… this twist of history has precisely to do… with the Gothic’s ‘origin’ as a counter-discourse to the modernizing impulse of the Enlightenment, and with postmodernism’s complex rebuttal and development of Modernism’s own post-Enlightenment progressive dictates.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T193209Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T193209Z">
        <seg>La distorsión de la perspectiva, que es un rasgo constante de la ficción gótica, encuentra un nuevo «hogar» en lo posmoderno y este giro de la historia tiene precisamente que ver con el «origen» del gótico como contradiscurso frente al impulso modernizador de la Ilustración, y con la compleja refutación y desarrollo del posmodernismo de lo que establece el propio progresismo posilustrado del modernismo (2004, p. 53).
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>pensar subj.</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The essential condition of this kind of love was that it had nothing to do^with marriage and could not possibly exist in marriage.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T220545Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T220545Z">
        <seg>La condición esencial de este tipo de amor era que no tenía nada que ver con el matrimonio y que, tal vez, no podría existir en el matrimonio. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The excesses and ambivalence associated with Gothic figures were seen as distinct signs of transgression.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T024558Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T024558Z">
        <seg>Se consideraban signos evidentes de transgresión a los excesos y a la ambivalencia asociados a las figuras góticas. 
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The excesses of political meaning display the ambivalence of Gothic.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023752Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023752Z">
        <seg>Los excesos del significado político muestran la ambivalencia del gótico. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The individualism in the novel is evident, as the narrative pivots around Ballard and the process of his becoming.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T194038Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T194038Z">
        <seg>El individualismo en la novela es evidente, ya que la narración gira en torno a Ballard y al proceso de su devenir.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The interplay reconﬁgures the signiﬁcance of Gothic horror in the postmodern world.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T154936Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T154936Z">
        <seg>La relación reconfigura el significado del terror gótico en el mundo posmoderno.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The literal meaning of the word *passion* will indicate the distance.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221517Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221517Z">
        <seg>El significado literal de la palabra “pasión” muestra esa distancia. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The novel traces the life and monstrous becoming of a rural Tennessee man called Lester Ballard, who gradually turns into a cave-dwelling serial killer and follows a path to ruin.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T161529Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T161529Z">
        <seg>La novela narra sobre la vida y la transformación monstruosa de un hombre rural de Tennesse llamado Lester Ballard, que se convierte de a poco en un asesino serial cavernícola y se encamina a la perdición. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>device</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The passages in which Humbert gives voice to this judgment are not as well done as one might wish; they stand in an awkward relation to the tone and device of the book.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T002530Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T002530Z">
        <seg>Los pasajes en los que Humbert da voz a este juicio no están tan bien logrados como uno podría desear; mantienen una relación incómoda con el tono y el recurso del libro.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The passion-lover was a sick man, a *patient.*</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221558Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221558Z">
        <seg>El amante apasionado era un hombre enfermo, un “paciente”.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The pervasive concern with identity could be summarized in Ballard’s reﬂection rendered in free indirect style when he watches “cold stars sprawled across the smokehole and wonder[s] what stuff they [are] made of, or himself” (p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T194003Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T194003Z">
        <seg>La preocupación constante por la identidad podría resumirse en la reflexión de Ballard, que se presenta en estilo indirecto libre al observar «frías estrellas esparcidas a través del hueco de humo y se pregunta de qué están hechas, o de qué está hecho él mismo» (p.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>calco</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The reason was that theirs was a practical and contractual relationship, having reference to estates and progeny.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T220631Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T220631Z">
        <seg>El motivo era que esa representaba una relación práctica y contractual, relacionada con los bienes y la descendencia.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The target of this parodic reprise of the *Bildungsroman* is speciﬁcally its reliance on such humanist notions as self-acculturation, self-empowering reason, mastery, social acceptance, and harmony.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200643Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200643Z">
        <seg>El objetivo de esta repetición paródica del Bildungsroman es específicamente su dependencia de nociones humanistas, en particular la autoaculturación, el motivo de autoempoderamiento, el dominio, la aceptación social y la armonía. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The term, however, was discussed in a more systematic manner by Morgenstern in another lecture entitled “On the Nature of the *Bildungsroman*” nine years later (Boes, 2012, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T211817Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203432Z">
        <seg>Sin embargo, Morgenstern analizó el término de manera más sistemática en otra conferencia titulada «Sobre la naturaleza del Bildungsroman», nueve años más tarde (Boes, 2012, p. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>The ‘solution’ proffered was to see discursive philosophy as a kind of category mistake.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T183018Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T183018Z">
        <seg>La «solución» propuesta consistió en considerar la filosofía discursiva como una suerte de error categórico. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Their behaviour to each other must be precisely not what we call “mature”—they must see each other and the world with the imperious absolutism of children.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260402T225003Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260402T225003Z">
        <seg>La conducta entre sí debe ser precisamente lo opuesto a lo que llamamos “madurez”, deben verse el uno al otro y ver el mundo con el absolutismo imperioso de los niños.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>pensar "then"</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Then the novelist must pay due attention to making the lover’s obsession believable and not ridiculous.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001127Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001127Z">
        <seg>Entonces, el novelista debe prestar atención a que la obsesión del amante resulte creíble y no ridícula.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>There is fundamental faith, Braidotti continues, “in the unique, self-regulating and intrinsically moral powers of human reason” embedded in the discourse of humanism (2013, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T191329Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T191329Z">
        <seg>Existe una fe fundamental, continúa Braidotti, «en los poderes singulares, autorregulados e intrínsecamente morales de la razón humana», inscrita en el discurso del humanismo (2013, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Redacción.
No remplazar asteriscos por comillas</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>There would follow a period in which husband and wife would each make an effort to get rid of their *merely symbolic* feelings for the other partner in the marriage and to learn to see each other *without illusion* and as they are *in reality*.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221319Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221319Z">
        <seg>Seguiría un período en el que marido y mujer se esforzarían por librarse de los sentimientos “meramente simbólicos” del uno hacia la otra, y por aprender a verse “sin ilusiones” y tal cual son “en realidad”. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Therefore, Ballard’s category crises are also degenerative as he passes through regressive stages of the posthuman, ultimately becoming an apparition to rematerialise in new shapes.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T201333Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T201333Z">
        <seg>Por lo tanto, las crisis de categorías de Ballard también son degenerativas, ya que atraviesa etapas regresivas de lo poshumano, convirtiéndose, al final, en una aparición que se rematerializa en nuevas formas.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>They are linked to wider threats of disintegration manifested most forcefully in political revolution.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023449Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023449Z">
        <seg>Éstas se vinculan con amenazas más amplias de desintegración, que se manifiestan con mayor fuerza en la revolución política. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>They could see no reason why a man could not break the chains of a passion so unrewarding, so humiliating.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001316Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001316Z">
        <seg>No veían razón para que un hombre no pudiera romper las cadenas de una pasión tan poco gratificante, tan humillante.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>This is the mode of</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001932Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001932Z">
        <seg>Este es el modo de adoración de </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>avisarme si hay segmentos mal cortados

ver colocación trasfondo. Acordar comillas.
ver comas</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>This is the mode of H. H.’s adoration of *Lolita*, and against the background of his sexual greed, whfch he calls “ape-like,” it comes over us as another reason for being shocked, that in recent fiction no lover has thought of his beloved with so much tenderness, that no woman has been so charmingly evoked, in such grace and delicacy, as Lolita; the description of her tennis game, in which even her racket has an erotic charm, is one of the few examples of rapture in modern writing.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Gabriel" changedate="20260407T170123Z" creationid="Gabriel" creationdate="20260407T170123Z">
        <seg>Este es el modo de adoración de H. H. hacia Lolita, y contra el trasfondo de su codicia sexual, que él llama «simiesca», nos impacta como otro motivo para escandalizarnos, que en la ficción más reciente ningún amante ha pensado en su amada con tanta ternura, que ninguna mujer ha sido evocada de manera tan encantadora, con tanta gracia y delicadeza, como Lolita; la descripción de su juego de tenis, en la que incluso su raqueta tiene un encanto erótico, es uno de los pocos ejemplos de éxtasis en la literatura moderna.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>This makes it unique in my experience of contemporary novels.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T215352Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T215352Z">
        <seg>Según mi experiencia en novelas contemporáneas, puedo afirmar que esta característica la vuelve única. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>usar ** para las cursivas.

Se pierde un how</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>This may not be quite fair to Mr. Nabokov’s whole intention, but it does suggest how regressive a book Lolita is, how, although it strikes all the most approved modern postures and attitudes, it is concerned to restore a foredone mode of feeling.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001730Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001730Z">
        <seg>Esto puede no ser del todo justo con el propósito del señor Nabokov, pero sí sugiere cuán regresivo es Lolita, y aunque adopta todas las posturas y actitudes modernas más apropiadas, se propone restaurar un modo de sentir ya superado.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>No unir.
Invertir S y P</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>This will suggest how far the modern ideal of love is from passion-love.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221503Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221503Z">
        <seg>lo que refleja lo alejado que el ideal moderno del amor se encuentra del amor apasionado.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Thus, *Child of God* can be interpreted as a postmodern parody of the tradition of the Bildungsroman in accordance with Linda Hutcheon’s deﬁnition of postmodern parody as “imitation characterized by ironic inversion” (2000, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200544Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200544Z">
        <seg>De este modo, Hijo de Dios puede interpretarse como una parodia posmoderna de la tradición del Bildungsroman, en conformidad con la definición de parodia posmoderna de Linda Hutcheon: «imitación caracterizada por la inversión irónica» (2000, p. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Thus, Ballard’s life becomes increasingly crowded with animals and then corpses, rather than an accommodating community of people.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T201207Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T201207Z">
        <seg>Así, la vida de Ballard se va poblando cada vez más de animales y luego de cadáveres, en lugar de una comunidad humana complaciente. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Thus, in lieu of progressing towards a better condition of life and positive social integration, which are often mirrored in and facilitated by the setting, the Gothic setting of *Child of God* is characterized by subversive degeneration consonant with the physical and psychological degeneration of the protagonist.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200925Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200925Z">
        <seg>Así, en lugar de avanzar hacia una mejor condición de vida y una integración social positiva, que a menudo se reflejan y se facilitan en el escenario, el espacio gótico de Hijo de Dios se caracteriza por una degeneración subversiva, acorde con la degeneración física y psicológica del protagonista. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>To achieve the foregoing, the novel fuses Gothic and postmodern elements into a synergy calibrated for the optimal representation of the horrid disintegration of a master narrative about humanity, namely humanism.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T200344Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T200344Z">
        <seg>Para ello, la novela fusiona elementos góticos y posmodernos en una sinergia planeada para la representación óptima de la desintegración hórrida de una metanarrativa sobre la humanidad, en concreto, el humanismo.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>sign vs señales</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>To do this is the sign of maturity.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221333Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221333Z">
        <seg>Estas acciones son señales de madurez, </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>polisemia de relación sexual</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Towards each other, as towards their children, they show *tolerance* and *understanding,* which they find it easier to do if they have a *good sexual relationship.*</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T221426Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T221426Z">
        <seg>Entre ellos y con los hijos, muestran “tolerancia” y “comprensión”, lo cual les resulta más fácil si tienen una “buena relación sexual”.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Uncertainties about the nature of power, law, society, family and sexuality dominate Gothic fiction.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T023422Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T023422Z">
        <seg>Las dudas sobre la naturaleza del poder, la ley, la sociedad, la familia y la sexualidad dominan la ficción gótica. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Vladimir Nabokov’s *Lolita* [^1]</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T214917Z" creationid="borrar" creationdate="20260402T131917Z">
        <seg> Lolita de Vladimir Nabokov</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>We with our modern latitude in these matters are likely to be amused by the minor details of his mistress’s person that caught the lover’s fancy in the novels of the nineteenth century—the expressiveness of the eyes, a certain kind of glance, a foot, an ankle, a wrist, an ear, a ringlet; with our modern reader’s knowledge of the size and shape of the heroine’s breasts, thighs, belly, and buttocks, these seem trifling and beside the point.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001815Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001815Z">
        <seg>Nosotros, con nuestra moderna laxitud en estos asuntos, tendemos a divertirnos con los detalles de menor importancia de la amada, aquellos que capturaban la fantasía del amante en las novelas del siglo XIX: la expresividad de los ojos, cierto tipo de mirada, un pie, un tobillo, una muñeca, una oreja, un bucle; para el lector moderno, que conoce el tamaño y la forma de los pechos, los muslos, el vientre y las nalgas de la heroína, estos detalles parecen triviales y fuera de lugar.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>Trasladar los ** para formar cursivas.</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>What I used to pamper among the tangled vines of my heart, *mon grand peche radieux*, had dwindled in its essence:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184847Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184847Z">
        <seg>Aquello que yo solía mimar entre las enredaderas de mi corazón, mon grand péché radieux, se había reducido en su esencia: </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>While this study refuses to reduce Western humanism to a caricature of the Enlightenment, its focus is mainly on the Enlightenment aspects of the humanist discourse, rather than the primarily pedagogical humanism of the Renaissance.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T191210Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T191210Z">
        <seg>Si bien este estudio se rehúsa a reducir el humanismo Occidental a una caricatura de la Ilustración, su foco recae principalmente en los aspectos ilustrados del discurso humanista, antes que en el humanismo primordialmente pedagógico del Renacimiento.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>"Y" o "Sin embargo". Invertir S y P.</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Yet it is always to marriage that passion-love aspires, unique marriage, ideal marriage, marriage available to no other pair, but marriage nonetheless, with all the cramping vows and habitualness of marriage.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Gabriel" changedate="20260407T171816Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184540Z">
        <seg>Y, sin embargo, es siempre hacia el matrimonio que el amor-pasión tiende: un matrimonio único, un matrimonio ideal, un matrimonio vedado a toda otra pareja, pero matrimonio al fin, con todos los votos constrictivos y la rutina que le son inherentes.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Yet narratives are dominated by values of family, domesticity and virtuous sentimentalism, values more appropriate to the middle-class readership that composed the increasingly large portion of the literary market in the eighteenth century.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260405T024112Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260405T024112Z">
        <seg>No obstante, los valores familiares, el ámbito doméstico y un sentimentalismo virtuoso dominaban las narraciones, valores más acordes con el lector de clase media, que constituía una porción cada vez mayor del mercado literario en el siglo XVIII. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Yet perhaps for that very reason they are the more startling and impressive (if we do not read them in a mood which makes them seem to verge upon the maudlin).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T002559Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T002559Z">
        <seg>Sin embargo, quizá por esa misma razón es que resultan aún más impactantes e impresionantes (si no los leemos en un estado de ánimo que los haga parecer rayanos a la sensiblería).
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <note>ver defining vs. non-defining
repensar v.p.
agregar passion-love al glosario</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>Yet the interest in the not immediately erotic details of the female person was not forced on the lover or the novelist by narrow conventions; rather, it was an aspect of the fetishism which seems to attend passion-love, a sort of synecdoche of desire, in which the part stands for the whole, and even the glove or the scarf of the beloved has an erotic value.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T001839Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T001839Z">
        <seg>Sin embargo, el interés por los detalles de la mujer, que no son propiamente eróticos, no era impuesto al amante ni al novelista por convenciones rígidas; más bien era un aspecto del fetichismo que parece acompañar al amor-pasión, una especie de sinécdoque del deseo, en la que la parte representa al todo, e incluso el guante o el pañuelo de la amada tiene un valor erótico.
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>You may jeer at me, and threaten to clear the court, but until I am gagged and halfthrottled, I will shout my poor truth.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184912Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184912Z">
        <seg>Podrían burlarse de mí y amenazar con desalojar la sala, pero mientras no me amordacen y me dejen a medio estrangular, gritaré mi pobre verdad. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>[^1]:From Speaking of Literature and Society.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T185300Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185239Z">
        <seg>[^1]: De “Speaking of Literature and Society”. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>but thank God it was not that echo alone that I worshipped.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184834Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184834Z">
        <seg>pero, gracias a Dios, no era solo ese eco lo que yo adoraba</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>only the *Bildungsroman* could overcome:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T182907Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T182907Z">
        <seg>solo el Bildungsroman podía resolver: </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>seem to remember he calls passion-love, a kind of love with which European literature has dealt since time immemorial but with especial intensity since the Arthurian romances and the code of courtly love.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260402T220451Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260402T220451Z">
        <seg>creo recordar que él llama amor pasional, una clase de amor con el que la literatura europea tuvo que lidiar desde siempre, pero con una intensidad especial desde los romances artúricos y el código del amor cortesano.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>speaks of the depth and wild solemnity of his love and remorse, Mr. Nabokov has not laid an emotional trap for the reader, that perhaps H. H.’s last intensities ought not to be received with considerably more irony than at first they call for.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T185103Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185103Z">
        <seg>habla de la profunda y la salvaje solemnidad de su amor y su remordimiento—, el Señor Vladimir Nabokov no haya tendido una trampa emocional al lector; que acaso las últimas intensidades de H. H. no debieran recibirse con bastante más ironía de la que en un primer momento parecen reclamar.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>sterile and selfish vice, all that I cancelled and cursed.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184901Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184901Z">
        <seg>vicio estéril y egoísta. Todo eso lo anulé y lo maldije.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>{.Quotation centered}
There she was with her ruined looks and her adult, rope-veined narrow hands and her gooseflesh white arms, and her shallow ears, and her unkempt armpits, there she was (my *Lolita*!), hopelessly worn at seventeen, with that baby, dreaming already in her of becoming a big shot and retiring around A.D.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T184743Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T184743Z">
        <seg>Allí estaba ella, con su aspecto arruinado y sus manos estrechas de mujer adulta, tensadas por venas como cuerdas, y sus brazos blancos erizados, y sus orejas poco profundas, y sus axilas descuidadas; allí estaba (¡mi Lolita!), irremediablemente marchitada a los diecisiete años, con ese bebé, soñando ya con hacerse alguien y retirarse hacia el año 2020 D.C </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>© 1958 by Lionel Trilling, © 1980 by Diana Trilling and James Trilling.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260403T185303Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260403T185303Z">
        <seg>© 1958 por Lionel Trilling, © 1980 por Diana Trilling y James Trilling.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>—(*Child of God*, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T161309Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T161309Z">
        <seg>(El hijo de Dios, pág. 58).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>“Concerning the Spirit and Cohesion of a Number of Philosophical Novels” delivered in 1810.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260403T203346Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260403T203346Z">
        <seg>«Sobre el espíritu y la cohesión de una serie de novelas filosóficas», según lo explica Tobias Boes. 
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>“Friedrich Hölderlin” in his *Poetry and Experience* as follows:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T193725Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T193725Z">
        <seg>«Friedrich Hölderlin» de su obra Poesía y experiencia, y que se transcriben a continuación:
</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>“Reckon you could do it now from watching?</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="A" changedate="20260407T160602Z" creationid="A" creationdate="20260407T160602Z">
        <seg>“¿Piensas que ahora lo puedes hacer luego de verlo? </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>“the logical domain of the novel of formation” (Boes, 2012, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T183207Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T183207Z">
        <seg>«el dominio lógico de la novela de formación» (Boes, 2012, p. </seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>ﬁction that can perform this task, not philosophy.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Soundwave" changedate="20260406T183050Z" creationid="Soundwave" creationdate="20260406T183050Z">
        <seg>ficción —y no la filosofía— la que puede llevar a cabo esta tarea</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>ﬂoundering “masternarratives about humanity” (Halberstam and Livingston, 1995, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="tg" changedate="20260404T174620Z" creationid="tg" creationdate="20260404T174620Z">
        <seg>las debatibles «metanarrativas sobre la humanidad» (Halberstam y Livingston, 1995, p.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
<!-- Alternative translations -->
    <tu>
      <prop type="file">04_Nanzer_Trilling_31-3.txt</prop>
      <prop type="prev">{.Quotation centered}</prop>
      <prop type="next">2020_ and I looked and looked at her, and knew as clearly as I know I am to die, that I loved her more than anything I had ever seen or imagined on earth, or hoped for anywhere else.</prop>
      <note>rope-veined: como cuerdas no es suficiente para armar la comparativa
poco profundas es mejorable
Discutir el !
</note>
      <tuv lang="en-US">
        <seg>There she was with her ruined looks and her adult, rope-veined narrow hands and her gooseflesh white arms, and her shallow ears, and her unkempt armpits, there she was (my *Lolita*!), hopelessly worn at seventeen, with that baby, dreaming already in her of becoming a big shot and retiring around A.D.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv lang="es-ES" changeid="Gabriel" changedate="20260407T173738Z" creationid="Gabriel" creationdate="20260407T172109Z">
        <seg>Allí estaba ella, con su aspecto arruinado y sus manos estrechas de mujer adulta, tensadas por venas como cuerdas, y sus brazos blancos erizados, y sus orejas poco profundas, y sus axilas descuidadas; allí estaba (¡mi Lolita!), irremediablemente marchitada a los diecisiete años, con ese bebé, soñando ya con hacerse alguien y retirarse hacia el año 2020 D.C.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
  </body>
</tmx>
